<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vaunting, daring, and a menacing letter, sent from Sultan Morat the great Turke, from his court at Constantinople, by his embassadour Gobam, to Vladisllaus King of Poland, &amp;c. Which letter was sent to the Christian King, since the truce concluded betweene the Turke and the Persian in March last; as by many copies whereof, may appeare, as it was sent out of Poland. Wherein he declares himselfe a mortall enemy to the said Christian King, threatning to invade his kingdomes and territories, with all manner of hostility. Whereunto is annexed a briefe relation of the Turkish present strength, both of horse and foote: with al the victories the Turkes have prevailed against the Christians these last three hundred yeares. As also what glorious victories the Christians have wonne against the Turkes, till this present yeare. 1638. Published by authority</title>
            <author>Murad IV, Sultan of the Turks, 1612-1640.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07915</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18286</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102874</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838636</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838636</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3022</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07915)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3022)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1146:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vaunting, daring, and a menacing letter, sent from Sultan Morat the great Turke, from his court at Constantinople, by his embassadour Gobam, to Vladisllaus King of Poland, &amp;c. Which letter was sent to the Christian King, since the truce concluded betweene the Turke and the Persian in March last; as by many copies whereof, may appeare, as it was sent out of Poland. Wherein he declares himselfe a mortall enemy to the said Christian King, threatning to invade his kingdomes and territories, with all manner of hostility. Whereunto is annexed a briefe relation of the Turkish present strength, both of horse and foote: with al the victories the Turkes have prevailed against the Christians these last three hundred yeares. As also what glorious victories the Christians have wonne against the Turkes, till this present yeare. 1638. Published by authority</title>
                  <author>Murad IV, Sultan of the Turks, 1612-1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. Okes, and are to be sold by I. Cowper at his shop at the east-end of St. Pauls Church, at the signe of the Holy Lambe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With an engraved frontispiece portrait of Murad IV.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Turkey --  History --  Murad IV, 1623-1640 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:3022:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>ILLUSTR: PRINCEPS SULTAN MORAT MAG<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> TURCARUM IMPERATOR ET CETERA</head>
                  <head>The Pourtraicture of the moſt Mightye Princ<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sultan Mora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Emperour of the Turkes now raigning: and brother to Achmat the laſt deceaced Emperour</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3022:1"/>
            <p>A Vaunting, Daring, and a Menacing Letter, Sent from <hi>Sultan Morat</hi> the great <hi>Turke,</hi> from his Court at <hi>Conſtantinople, by his</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour <hi>Gobam,</hi> to <hi>Vladiſllaus</hi> King of <hi>Poland, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which Letter was ſent to the Chriſtian King, ſince the Truce concluded betweene the</hi> Turke <hi>and the</hi> Perſian <hi>in</hi> March laſt; as <hi>by many Copies whereof, may appeare, as it was ſent out of Poland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein he declares himſelfe a mortall Enemy to the ſaid Chriſtian King, threatning to invade his Kingdomes and Territories, with all manner of Hoſtility.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is annexed a briefe Relation of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> preſent ſtrength, both of Horſe and Foote: with al the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictories the Turkes have prevailed againſt the Chriſtians theſe laſt three hundred yeares.</p>
            <p>As alſo what glorious Victories the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> have wonne againſt the <hi>Turkes,</hi> till this preſent yeare. 1638.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed by <hi>I. Okes,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>I. Cowper</hi> at his Shop at the Eaſt-end of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church, at the Signe of the <hi>Holy Lambe.</hi> 1638.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:3022:2"/>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>ſtigations of Sathan, there hath none prevailed ſo much for the enlarging and increaſe of his Infernall Kingdome, as the ſetting of Chriſtian Kings and Princes at variance one againſt the other, and the whilſt they have beene by the eares (as it were) and infeſting each other with deadly hatred and bloody Warres, the <hi>Turke,</hi> their common Adverſary, hath taken advantage of their unnaturall diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and by force taken from them (in little more than three Hundred yeeres paſt) more Kingdomes, Empires, Principalities, large Territories and Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niories, from the Chriſtians, than all the reſt of Chriſtendome beſides. His force and power I will partly relate in the latter end of this Treatiſe, and alſo how the Chriſtians have oftentimes had the better of him, when they have beene at Unity and peace amongſt themſelves: but firſt let the Reader peruſe the true Coppy of an inſulting proud Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, lately ſent from the Grand Signior from his Court at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to the King of <hi>Poland</hi> now Reigning; the Contents of the <hi>Letter</hi> were as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:3022:2"/>
            <head>The true Coppy of a Letter of <hi>Denyall of Peace, ſent from the</hi> Turkiſh Emperor to the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> as by many Coppies here in <hi>England,</hi> may appeare.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>SUltan Morat,</hi> or <hi>Amurah,</hi> the fourth of that Name, by the Grace of the Great God in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the onely Monarch of the World, a great and mighty God on Earth, an invincible <hi>Caeſar,</hi> King of all Kings from the <hi>Eaſt</hi> unto the <hi>Weſt,</hi> High and Mighty Emperour of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> doe by theſe our Imperiall Letters ſignifie to thee <hi>Uladiſlaus,</hi> King of <hi>Poland,</hi> how that our Highneſſe, by our truſty and wel-beloved Embaſſador <hi>Goban,</hi> formerly made Articles, Agreements, and Conditions of Peace, which now we utterly deny and renounce, by reaſon wee have received certaine Intelligence and true Knowledge at our Imperiall Court, that thou haſt and doeſt dayly make private Contracts, not onely with our revolting and rebellious Subjects, but alſo with our mortall Enemy the perfidious <hi>Moſcovite:</hi> And furthermore thou haſt contemptuouſly ſleighted and ſcorned our Great and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nconquerable forces, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3022:3"/>no more account of them than triviall things of ſmall valew, or little eſteeme; relieving and wholly depending upon thy owne ſtrength and power, which is but weake and feeble in reſpect of our Invincible Hoſtes, and huge Armies and Forces, which we dayly doe maintaine, being both Horſe and Foot. We ſee that the Reflexion of the Grace and Favour which we have beene pleaſed of our magnificent and aboundant goodneſſe to reflect upon thee, and by the peace which we have ſuffred and vouchſafed thee by our Clemency (undeſerved) to enjoy, thou having formerly ſworne and promiſed to keepe good correſpondent League and Amity with us, with our Friends and Confederates: which Promiſes of thine (out of thine owne Pride &amp; Inſolence) thou haſt not performed, but moſt falſely broken and violated; which we will no longer ſuffer to goe without Correction and Acknowledgment: For by the reaſon of thy refractory falling off from wee, there are other petty Kings and Princes, (who by thy inſtigation) doe combine together, and offer to take up Armes, and ſtand in defiance againſt me and my power, truſting upon their handfulls of men and weak Fortifications.</p>
            <p>Moreover, thou art willing, and with readineſſe doeſt watch all opportunities to make more Contracts with other Kings, that they alſo would aſſiſt thee; and deſie us: But if thou doeſt perſiſt in thy ambitious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions and deſignes; then know, that for everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting time; neither thy ſelfe or any of thy Succeſſors (the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Kings) ſhall never have Peace or Amity with us, or the ſucceeding <hi>Othoman</hi> Empire: but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3022:3"/>thou art to expect nothing but utter ruine, ſlaughter, and all the calamities of a juſt incenſed conquering Adverſary to fall upon thee; wee will enter thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and thy other Signiories with our forcible and innumerable Armies, and there ſhall be no mercy to be expected from our hands. I would have thee know that ſince that long and bloody Warre is ended, &amp; that now there is Peace concluded for <hi>21.</hi> yeers to come, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene us &amp; the <hi>Perſian</hi> Emperor, that not only thou but other of thy adherents ſhall not be ſuffered in their inſolent wayes to perſiſt, but that I will wholly bend and ſet my innumerable Army upon thee and them.</p>
            <p>Thou didſt promiſe according to our former agreements, to live quietly, and at Peace, which now thou neglecteſt, and regardeſt not, but haſt let looſe thy licentious will; and thy cut-throate <hi>Coſſacks</hi> and <hi>Heiducks,</hi> like Hell-hounds, doe fall in and make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſions into our confines and Territories, in divers parts of our Empire, plundering and ſpoyling my people in that Hoſtile manner upon thy unlawfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and unadviſed want of fore-ſight, which we will revenge in the higheſt and ſevereſt meaſure that we poſſibly can imagine or execute. Alſo upon thy intemperate will and pleaſure thou wouldſt have cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed our truſty and well-beloved Embaſſador <hi>(Abbas, Baſſa)</hi> to take ſome diſtaſte againſt our Imperiall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and State, which was an injury inſufferable, and it was the occaſion that his Loyalty to us, made him fall upon thee, in the defence of mine honour, in my Name, and behalfe, which thou at that time didſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuouſly ſeeme to ſleight alſo.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:3022:4"/>
            <p>And doſt thou now, (after all theſe uncivill Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies) deſire Peace? which is becauſe thou heareſt of a mighty great Army, which I have cauſed to be levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd raiſed, which I purpoſe ſhall fall heavie upon thee and thy weake Forces with all poſſible ſpeed; yea, our invincible <hi>Ianizaries,</hi> whoſe often tryed valour and ſtrength ſhall make thee and the whole World to tremble; beſides our <hi>Tartarian</hi> Horſe-men, who ſhall meete thee in the wide Fields, and toſſe thee and thy weake forces like duſt or aſhes in the Aire, or motes in the Sunne; my invincible powers of Foote and Horſe (whoſe numbers thou ſhalt not be able to count) like a huge Mountaine ſhall over-top thee, like a raging Torrent overturne thee, and like a violent Inunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion overwhelme thee, with mercileſſe plundering, robbing, ſpoyling, waſting, and burning both thy Countrey and people. Then ſhalt thou know (with great feare and dread) my force and power, nay, all thy Adherents and Confederates, (be they whom they will, in number never ſo many) ſhall quake and tremble at my dreadfull and juſt indignation: It is not thy Kingdome of <hi>Poland,</hi> thy Principality of <hi>Lithuania,</hi> thy <hi>Ruſſes, Goths,</hi> and <hi>Vandails,</hi> nor any of thy Countries and Dominions, which thou patſt ſo much unſtable ſecurity and confidence in, (with all their beſt defences for themſelves, or oppoſition of us) that altogether ſhall be able for the ſpace of one Moneth to endure the force of my might and power: The ſwelling Seas ſhall ſhrinke under the burthen and weight of our unparalell'd Shipping, when our Navy Royall and Tryumphant ſhall glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3022:4"/>ſhew it ſelfe upon the vaſt Ocean; namely, our Gallyes, Gallyaſſes, Argoſies, Friggots, and Brigan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines, when they ſhew themſelves on the Seas, the land ſhall admire, and the wilde beaſts of the Forreſts ſhall ſhake, and fearefully runne into obſcure holes, dennes, and cavernes of the earth, when they doe heare the terrible report of our thundring Ordnance diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged.</p>
            <p>And what wilt thou doe then, thou petty King, with thy poore, and weak Bands and Troopes, or handfuls of men, when thou ſhalt behold my great and powerfull Armies, which ſhall cover thy Countries: Thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nting ſhew, and art ſeemingly-confident in thy ever-weening opinion, that thou canſt conſume and deſtroy the great Waſpe with a ſmall Gnat: Know thou, that our ſtrength and terrour doth reach and extend further than our ample Dominions, for our Imperiall commanding name is dreadfull, and famous through the whole World, or Vniverſall Globe of the Earth, from the riſing of the Sunne, to the ſetting of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Wee purpoſe (with the edges of our ſharpe and well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered Semiters) to loppe and mow downe thy am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and to ruinate the oſtentatious pride of thee, and thy Countrey. And we aſſure thee, that it is meere folly for thee to expect any Peace, Truce, or League with us, after wee have once ſet footing in thy Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories: for our holy Prophet <hi>Mahomet</hi> is highly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at our ſo long Clemency, in forbearing and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring thee in thy ungodly and wilfull actions. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we will come to <hi>Craconia,</hi> (thy Metropolis and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3022:5"/>chiefe Citty in <hi>Poland</hi>) in the ſtrength of which place thou putteſt much confidence; and where (as we are lately certified) thou haſt built a holy Sepulchre, in imitation of that which we have in poſſeſſion in the ſacred City of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> upon which thou doſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe rely; but that neither can, nor ſhall helpe thee; for we will raze and overthrow your Temples, Churches, and Chappels, and convert them into Turkiſh Moskies, for the ſervice of our holy Prophet; and thoſe whom our force and fury doe not demoliſh and confound, wee will turne into Stables, where our Horſes and Cammels ſhall live, and be houſed with rack and manger: Thus we (the great God of the World) determine to doe; theſe fore-threatned miſteries thou muſt expect; and it is not thy Crucified God (in whom thou putteſt thy confidence) that ſhall helpe thee; for we purpoſe, that when our ſword is once drawne, not to ſheath it again, till we have made a finall conqueſt of Chriſtendome, or utter extirped and chaſed them from, or neare any parts of our Dominions.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Sent by our truſty Servant and Embaſſadour in the Ides of the Moneth of March.</hi> Anno <hi>1637.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:3022:5"/>
            <p>THus may the Reader perceive in what thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering manner, and oſtentatious boaſting, this great and and ſea <hi>Leviathan</hi> threatneth to overthrow and devoure the <hi>Polonian</hi> King; but that manner of inſulting and vaine-glorious wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from the Turke, to Chriſtian Princes, is no newes in theſe dayes of ours: for if any man will but looke into the famous, and well written Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Hiſtory, (now newly printed by Maſter <hi>Adam Iſlip,</hi> in the 300 Page hee may reade how the Turk <hi>Amurath,</hi> the ſixth King of the Turkes, writes to <hi>Scanderbeg,</hi> or <hi>George Caſtriot,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iohn Caſtriot,</hi> King of <hi>Albania</hi> or <hi>Epirus.</hi> Alſo if you looke into the 1024 Page of the aforeſaid booke, you may read of a braving Letter (farre ſurpaſſing this here before mentioned) ſent from <hi>Amurath,</hi> the third Emperour of the Turkes, to <hi>Rodolphus</hi> the ſecond Emperour of <hi>Germany,</hi> where in that place may be ſeene the moſt impious and blaſphemous threatnings, that ever Heathen, Infidell, or Athei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall <hi>Barbarian</hi> hath belched or vomited againſt either God or man. But for a proud Letter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, looke in the 789 Page, and there you may read the Maſter-piece of a vaunting title, which <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liman,</hi> the Magnificent Emperour of the Turkes, ſent to <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Emperour of <hi>Germany,</hi> in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3022:6"/>the yeare 1561. there you may perceive that the Stiles and Titles which the Turke gives himſelfe, would, of it ſelfe, fill halfe a Pamphlet: (in procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation Print) But Chriſtian Princes who doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that they doe hold their Crownes and Scepters from, and under God, and his ſonne <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> are more ſtrongly fortifi'd with heavenly Faith, and Majeſtical courage, than to be ſear'd or afrighted with Bugge-beare words, or farre-fetch'd large emboſt, and embroydered Stiles or Titles.</p>
            <p>And for one inſtance of the juſt Titles of a Prince, who was indeede, in his greateſt Stile but an Arch-Duke of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> yet in reall repetitions of the Signiories, over which he was lawfull Lord, and poſſeſſor: he was (in his time) Equivalent, that was then reigning in the whole Chriſtian World. He lived in the yeare 1494, and his Titles were as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The many, juſt, and ample Stiles and Titles of <hi>Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgundy.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Philip,</hi> by the grace of God, Arch-Duke of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgundy, Lothier, Brabant, Stiria, Carinthia, Lemburgh, Lupenburgh,</hi> and <hi>Guelders;</hi> Earle of <hi>Hauſpergh, Flanders, Arthoys, Burgoigne, Ferrets,</hi> and <hi>Kiburgh;</hi> Palatine of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nault, Holland, Zealand, Namure,</hi> and <hi>Zutphen,</hi> Marqueſſe of the <hi>Holy Empire,</hi> and of <hi>Burgan;</hi> Lantſgrave of <hi>Elſaten;</hi> Lord of <hi>Windeſmarke, Portevan, Salines,</hi> and <hi>Macklin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although the repetition of this great Chriſtian
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3022:6"/>Princes Title may ſeeme ſomewhat impertinent, yet it may be taken as tollerable, becauſe in a good meaſure it ſhews that there hath beene, are, and will be Kings and Princes in Chriſtendome, that can vye Titles, and dare wage Warre with the <hi>Turke,</hi> and firſt I will a little demonſtrate the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and after declare how hee hath beene often foyled and beaten.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Otheman,</hi> the firſt King of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> wonne many Caſtles and Territories from the Chriſtians in <hi>Greece;</hi> as <hi>Cara Chiſar, Chalce, Belezuge, Jarchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar, Nice, Neapolis, Pruſa,</hi> (or <hi>Buruſa.</hi>) This <hi>Otho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> overcame the valiant <hi>Grecian</hi> Emperour <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael,</hi> in the Countrey of <hi>Thrace,</hi> in an unfortunate mortall Battell: After that <hi>Othoman</hi> (in another Battell in <hi>Cherſoneſus</hi>) overcame the Chriſtian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, and conquer'd and plundred almoſt all <hi>Thracia,</hi> with many other places of ſtrength, which he wonne from the Chriſtians: <hi>Othoman</hi> Reigned in the yeere of our Lord 1327, at which time <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the third was King of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Orchanes,</hi> the ſecond King of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> wonne from the Chriſtians <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> and likewiſe the Kingdome of <hi>Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſia</hi> or <hi>Carafina,</hi> which contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Lydia,</hi> part of <hi>Miſia,</hi> part of <hi>Phrygia</hi> the leſſe, with <hi>Troas</hi> and the City of <hi>Pergamus,</hi> a moſt migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Kingdome: After that hee wonne the ſtrong Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of <hi>Maditus,</hi> and the goodly City of the <hi>Callipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis. Orchanes</hi> got moſt of all theſe in one yeere from the Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amurath,</hi> the firſt of that Name, and third King
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3022:7"/>of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> wonne from the Chriſtians many Countreys and Cities, of which Cities <hi>Hadrianople</hi> in <hi>Europe</hi> was the chiefe, where hee after kept his Court, which was then made the Royall Seate for the <hi>Turkes</hi> in <hi>Europe. Amurath</hi> invaded and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered <hi>Servia,</hi> ſlew <hi>Lazarus</hi> the Prince or Deſpot of that large Countrey; wonne a great part of <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garia;</hi> and many other places. He Reigned <hi>Anno</hi> 1377. when <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond was King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bajazet,</hi> the firſt of that Name, and fourth King of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> wonne <hi>Philadelphia</hi> from the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; he ſpoyled the Countrey of <hi>Valachia,</hi> and made it Tributary to him: He deſtroyed <hi>Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> and all <hi>Theſſaly;</hi> hee overthrew the Chriſtian Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my at the unfortunate battell of <hi>Nicopolis, Sigiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund</hi> King of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> having 130000. Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Horſe and Foote almoſt all loſt. Alſo <hi>Bajazet</hi> wonne the moſt part of <hi>Capadocia:</hi> he Reigned <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1399. when <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth was King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> This <hi>Bajazet</hi> was at the laſt overcome, and taken priſoner by <hi>Tomberlaine,</hi> and loſt much of what his predeceſſors had wonne. All which and more was recovered againe by his Succeſſor <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met,</hi> the firſt of that Name, and firſt King of the <hi>Turkes: Mahomet</hi> reigned <hi>Anno</hi> 1413, when <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth was King of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amurah,</hi> the ſecond of that name, and ſixth King of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> with a mighty and mercileſſe Army ſpoyled and plundred the moſt part of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> he ſubdued <hi>Servia,</hi> hee waſted the Principality of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3022:7"/>
               <hi>Tranſilvania:</hi> he overcame and ſlew the <hi>Hungarian</hi> and <hi>Pol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nian</hi> King <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ladiſlaus,</hi> and conquer'd a great part of <hi>Hungaria;</hi> he waſted the large Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of <hi>Peloponeſus,</hi> (now called <hi>Morea</hi>) and after hee had filled a great many Chriſtian Kingdomes and Lordſhips with blood-ſlaughter, and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of cruelties, he having reigned 28. yeares, in the yeare of Grace 1448, or thereabouts, when <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt was King of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mahomet</hi> the ſecond of that Name, the ſeventh King, and firſt Emperour of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> for his many victories and conqueſts called <hi>Mahomet</hi> the Great: Hee wonne the famous City of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> from the Chriſtians, on the 29. of <hi>May,</hi> 1453. It had anciently beene the Royall ſeat of the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne or <hi>Grecian</hi> Emperours, where ever ſince the <hi>Othoman</hi> Family hath placed their Imperial Courts. Hee conquer'd the City and Empire of <hi>Trapezond, Anno</hi> 1461. In the time of 31. yeares which hee reigned, hee got from the Chriſtians one Empire, 12. Kingdomes, and 200. Cities; hee dyed when <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth was King of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bajazet</hi> the ſecond of that Name, the Eighth King, and ſecond Emperour of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded <hi>Moldavia,</hi> hee wonne the City of <hi>Tarſus</hi> in <hi>Cilicia,</hi> (where St. <hi>Paul</hi> was borne) he made fierce inroads into <hi>Podolia</hi> and <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> ſpoyled the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of <hi>Friulli,</hi> which was the <hi>Venetians;</hi> alſo hee tooke from them the great Cities of <hi>Lepanto, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> or <hi>Methone, Corone, Pilus, Dirrachium;</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hee had for 30. yeeres ſpace of his Reigne done
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3022:8"/>all the miſchiefe he could to Chriſtendome, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very aged, was by the command of <hi>Selimus,</hi> his moſt undutifull ſonne, who corrupted a Jew, that was his Fathers Phyſitian, poyſoned, <hi>Anno</hi> 1509. when <hi>Henry</hi> the eight was King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Selimus,</hi> the firſt of that name, the ninth King of the Turkes, and third Emperour, he invaded ſome parts of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> and after eight yeeres of a cruell bloody reigne, he dyed of a canker in his backe, which yeelded ſuch a ſtench, that long before his deceaſe, no man durſt come neare him: He was ſo buſied in his warres with the <hi>Perſians, Arabians. Armenians,</hi> and <hi>Egyptians,</hi> that he had but little leaſure to moleſt the Chriſtians; hee dyed in the yeare of our Redemption 1520, <hi>Henry</hi> the eight then being King of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Soliman,</hi> ſurnamed the <hi>Magnificent,</hi> the tenth King, and fourth Emperour of the Turkes, hee wan from the Knights of the order of Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> the famous Iſland of the <hi>Rhodes,</hi> on Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas day, <hi>Anno</hi> 1522: he overthrew the <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> in a mortall battaile, at a place called <hi>Mohat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaz,</hi> where amongſt thouſands of common Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, many of the nobility of that Countrey were ſlaine; and King <hi>Lewis</hi> (King of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) ſeeking to ſave himſelfe by flight, was moſt miſerably drowned in a Ditch; and he carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away more than one hundred and fifty thouſand poore Chriſtians with him in that expedition out of <hi>Hungaria</hi> to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> 1526: After that, he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3022:8"/>entred <hi>Hungaria</hi> again, &amp; wan the ſtrong City and Caſtle of <hi>Buda,</hi> and ſpoyled a great part of <hi>Auſtria:</hi> And in the yeare 1532, he entred the ſecond time into <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and moſt cruelly burnt, ſpoyl'd, and waſted the Countrey, filling it full of blood and ſlaughter, and carrying away many people into perpetuall ſlavery. By his admirable <hi>Barbaruſſa</hi> he did much ſpoyle to the <hi>Venetians,</hi> and did much miſchiefe to the <hi>Italians:</hi> Hee alſo ſpoyled the rich and beautifull Countrey of <hi>Apulia:</hi> hee like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe invaded the Iſland of <hi>Corcira,</hi> and from cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine other Iſles and places in <hi>Italy,</hi> carryed away 16000 poore Chriſtians into Captivity to <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> 1537. He conquered the rich Iſlands of <hi>Napos</hi> and <hi>Aegina;</hi> after that he overthrew <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand</hi> King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> with a great ſlaughter; hee beate the Chriſtian Fleete, or Navy, ſet forth at the charges of <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, Emperour of <hi>Germany, Paul</hi> the third, Pope or Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the <hi>Venetians</hi> 1539. After that he wan the ſtrong Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Buda</hi> in <hi>Hungaria,</hi> 1540. In the yeare 1543, <hi>Soliman</hi> came with a huge army againe into <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garia,</hi> meaning to over-runne the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; then he beſieged, and won the moſt ſtrong and great Cities of <hi>Strigonium,</hi> and <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> wherein he uſed all kinde of cruelties that could be imagined. He wonne the City of <hi>Tripolis</hi> in <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barie</hi> from the Chriſtians; and in the yeare 1566 he tooke the rich and fertile Iſland of <hi>Chios.</hi> Thus <hi>Soliman,</hi> having bin a mighty Invador and ſpoyler of Chriſtendome, after 44. yeares reigne dyed, in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3022:9"/>the eighth yeare of the Reigne of the unmatchable, famous, and vertuous <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Queene of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> 1566.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Selimus,</hi> the ſecond of that name, the eleventh King, and firſt Emperour of the Turkes, conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and tooke the rich Iſland and Kingdome of <hi>Ciprus,</hi> from the <hi>Venetians;</hi> he made great Havock in the Countrey of <hi>Moldavia,</hi> and <hi>Vallachia,</hi> and in other parts of Chriſtendome, with the extreameſt barbarous cruelties, as ever was inflicted, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eight years of his bloody and tyrannicall reigne, waſted in his fleſh and ſpirits, and amply furniſhed with diſeaſes, which are eaſily purchaſed with drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe and leacherie, hee dyed <hi>Anno</hi> 1574. The famous <hi>Elizabeth</hi> then being Queene of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amurath,</hi> the third of that name, the twelfth King, and ſixth Emperour of the Turkes, he was almoſt wholly buſied in the warres againſt the Princes of the Eaſterne parts of the World, as the <hi>Perſians, Arabians, Armenians,</hi> and others of the Orientall Nations, ſo that he had very little leaſure to make any warres or inroads into Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, although he with threats and braving menacings, made large promiſes to invade the Chriſtians: but haved reigned nineteene yeares, he dyed of the Stone, and the falling ſickneſſe, in the yeare of grace 1595, in the 37 yeare of the reigne of <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the admired Queene of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mahomet,</hi> the third of that name, the thirteenth
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3022:9"/>King, and ſeventh Emperour of the Turkes, had many bloody and cruell battailes, and bickerings with the Chriſtians, in <hi>Hungaria, Tranſilvania Vallachia, Stiria, Moldavia, Auſtria,</hi> and in divers places of the <hi>Germane</hi> Empire: He wonne, and loſt, and by his Baſſaes, Lievtenants, and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, did beate, and were beaten: he dyed, <hi>Anno</hi> 1604, in the third yeare of the reigne of King <hi>Iames</hi> of bleſſed memory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Achmat,</hi> the foureteenth King, and eighth Emperour of the Turkes; He, by his Baſſa, aided with the <hi>Tartars,</hi> ſpoyled the upper <hi>Hungaria,</hi> there they tooke and ranſacked the townes of <hi>Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin, Tregla, Puganiſa, Iarmeta, Samoſchin, Regim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat, Palanka, Dillena, Sacmaria, Rabenſtine, Onoth, Vacia, Sevara, Blavenſtine, Tabra, Diſgiora, Libetua, Calo, Sitna, Nagibana, Scharoſpotac, Zatuar, Filek, Budnoc,</hi> with many other ſtrong townes and places both in <hi>Hungaria,</hi> and <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> which were ſack'd and ſpoyled by the Turkes, through the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, rebellions, and treacheries of falſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; ſometimes the Governours and Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders were corrupted with gifts, given them by the Turkes; and many times the Chriſtian Souldiers revolting, and in mutiny for pay; and in the yeare 1605 the famous and ſtrong City of <hi>Strigonium,</hi> in <hi>Hungaria,</hi> was taken by the Turkes: But in the yeare 1606, a peace was concluded betwixt the great <hi>Sultan,</hi> and the <hi>German</hi> Emperour, ſince which time there hath no matters of great Hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity beene uſed on either ſide. <hi>Achmat</hi> dyed when he had reigned fifteene yeares, <hi>Anno,</hi> 1617.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3022:10"/>in the 15. yeere of the Reigne of King <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Muſtapha</hi> the Fourteenth King, and Ninth Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> was the Brother to <hi>Achmat</hi> deceaſed; he had no great time in his firſt Reigne, either to make or move Peace or Warre, for hee was depoſed, and put into a Cell at or neare the end of two Moneths after his Coronation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oſman,</hi> the ſonne of the afore-named <hi>Achmat,</hi> the Fifteenth King of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> and Tenth Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, in the yeere 1620, the <hi>Turkes</hi> with a great power made Warre by Sea upon the Kingdome of <hi>Naples,</hi> where they wonne the City of <hi>Manfredo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> and after they had moſt miſerably ſack'd it, they carried away neare 1500. poore Chriſtians in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to intollerable ſlavery. <hi>Oſman</hi> gives occaſions of diſtaſte, and grievances to the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> by conniving craftily, and ſuffering the <hi>Tartars</hi> to make inroads into divers parts of <hi>Polonia,</hi> for which indignitie the <hi>Polonian</hi> King did make the like incurſions into the <hi>Turkes</hi> Dominions, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that it grew to a Warre; ſo that the <hi>Turkes</hi> entred <hi>Poland</hi> with a great Army, whence hee car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away 25000. Chriſtians as ſlaves to <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople:</hi> After which a Peace was concluded betwixt the <hi>Grand Signior</hi> and the <hi>Pole</hi> 1622, and in the yeere 1623. <hi>Sultan Oſman</hi> was treacherouſly and trayterouſly ſtrangled and murder'd by the Great <hi>Viſier</hi> named <hi>Daut Baſſa,</hi> after which the depoſed <hi>Muſtapha</hi> was againe crowned the ſecond time, and in leſſe than Nine Moneths after hee was made the mockery of Fortune, and depoſed the ſecond time from his Imperiall dignity; but what became of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3022:10"/>him afterwards, I have neither read or heard of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Morat</hi> or <hi>Amurath,</hi> the ſixteenth King, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leventh Emperour of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> (now reigning) was on the laſt of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1623. crowned: hee was the ſonne of <hi>Sultan Achmat,</hi> and hath kept the peace for the moſt part with all Chriſtian Kings and Princes, but hee hath had his hands full with the <hi>Perſian,</hi> and with ſome others of his owne <hi>Baſſaes</hi> which have fallen into rebellion againſt him.</p>
            <p>To ſhew the Numbers of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Foote and Horſe, which he hath dayly at continuall command in all places of his Dominions at all times, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation would either beheld to be incredible, or the <hi>Turkes</hi> power to be invincible, both which opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of people are ſcarce worth the refuting; for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience knowes they are both falſe.</p>
            <p>Yet the ſtrong City of <hi>Scodra</hi> in <hi>Dulmalia</hi> (bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering on <hi>Epirus</hi> and <hi>Albania</hi>) was beſieged in the yeare 1473. by the <hi>Turkes</hi> Army in number 350000 men and Horſe; there was 12000. Camells laden with Braſſe in Maſſe or hunos, which they caſt into great Ordinance, ſo great indeed as never the like were heard or read of; for it is truely reported, that one Gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne carried a Bullet of 300. pound weight, and that two other Peeces carried Bullets of 400. weight, one carried a ſhot of 650. weight, and one which they called the Princes Peece, carried a Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let of 1200. weight; and laſtly, another carried a ſhot of 1300. weight. He had alſo at that Siege as many Braſſe-peeces for Battery, as made up the full number of 178, and after ſixe moſt ſharpe and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Aſſaults, and a whole yeeres ſiege it was
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3022:11"/>through want enforced to yeeld upon Compoſition to the <hi>Turkes.</hi> Read the Turkiſh Hiſtory, <hi>pag.</hi> 421.</p>
            <p>The Great <hi>Sultan</hi> hath Horſe-men called <hi>Tima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots,</hi> which are Gentlemen that hold Lands of him during their lives, and they are for every 60. Duckats of yeerely value or Rent of thoſe Lands to maintaine one Horſe and a man armed with a Bow, Arrows, Semitar, Target, and Launce, as well in Peace as in Warre: Hee, whoſe Land is worth but 60. Duckats, muſt finde one; hee that hath 120. Dukats, muſt maintaine 2. Horſmen ſo armed; and ſo of the reſt: theſe <hi>Timariots</hi> are diſperſt all over his Dominions, and are, as is truely related, in number 719000.</p>
            <p>To ſpeake of his potent <hi>Baſſaes,</hi> his great <hi>Begler bags,</hi> his commanding <hi>Sanzacks,</hi> his inſolent <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizaries,</hi> his mutinous <hi>Spahi,</hi> his ruſticke <hi>Acanzij Horſe-men, his innumerable unregarded Aſapi,</hi> it is ſo well deſcribed by many worthy. Authors, but eſpecially in the fore-named Hiſtory of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> to which I refer the Reader for ample ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>And although what hath beene in this briefe Treatiſe related, hath onely ſhewed the conqueſts greatneſſe, power, and ſtrength of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> how they have beaten and overcome the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in ſundry Battells, bloody foughten-fields, Sieges, and Sallies: yet it is not amiſie to ſhew when, where, and how hee hath beene from time to time repulſt, and beaten both by the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and alſo by other Princes and Potentates of his owne <hi>Mahomet an</hi> Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition.</p>
            <p>In the yeare of our Lord 1397. <hi>Tamberlane</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3022:11"/>threw <hi>Bajazet</hi> the firſt,<note place="margin">How, when, and by whom the <hi>Turkes</hi> have beene o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrowne oftentimes.</note> and the fourth King of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> in a mortall Battell, where <hi>Bajazet</hi> with his ſon <hi>Muſa</hi> were taken Priſoners, and the proud <hi>Turke</hi> was ſhut up in an Iron Cage by <hi>Tamberlane,</hi> and in that Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell 300000. <hi>Turkes</hi> were ſlaine, in which thraldome he endured two yeeres, and then (in the pride of his heart and greatneſſe of ſpirit) ended his miſerable life, and violently beate out his owne braines againſt the Cage, <hi>Anno</hi> 1399.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amurath</hi> the ſecond beſieged <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and was moſt bravely repulſt and beaten thence <hi>Anno</hi> 1439, and in the ſame yeere he was (with a great ſlaughter, and loſſe of many Thouſands of his men and Horſe, beaten from the Siege of <hi>Belgrade</hi> in <hi>Hungaria:</hi> The valiant Chriſtian Prince <hi>Huniades</hi> (Vaivod of <hi>Tranſilvania</hi>) in two ſeverall Battells overthrew <hi>Iſa Beg</hi> the <hi>Turkes</hi> Cene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall in <hi>Servia,</hi> and ſlew <hi>Meſites Baſſa</hi> and his ſonne, with more than 30000. <hi>Turkes</hi> in both battells, for which loſſes <hi>Amurath</hi> was ſo mad, that hee was about to have killed himſelfe: but being perſwaded to patience, hee ſurrendred the whole government of his Empire, and retired himſelfe into a Cell, or Houſe of Religion: Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards he re-aſſumed his eſtate, and though hee won the Battell of <hi>Varna</hi> 1444, in which <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ladiſlaus</hi> King of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> was ſlaine, yet the Chriſtians ſold their lives at ſo deare a rate, that 30000. of the <hi>Turkes</hi> were there ſlaine. After that the valiant <hi>Scanderbeg,</hi> (<hi>aliàs George Caſtriot</hi>) King of <hi>Epirus</hi> and <hi>Albania,</hi> he recover'd his Kingdomes from the <hi>Turke;</hi> hee beate <hi>Alis Baſha,</hi> and ſlew 22000. of them, and tooke 760. priſoners. In a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Battell he vancuiſh'd <hi>Ferſes Baſha,</hi> and put him to flight with the loſſe of 3000. men, and many priſoners
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3022:12"/>taken. Hee overthrew the <hi>Baſha Muſtapha</hi> in a battell; and ſlew 5000. <hi>Turkes,</hi> and tooke 300. priſoners, 1445. Alſo in the yeare 1448. <hi>Huniades</hi> fought the great bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell of <hi>Coſſova,</hi> which laſted three dayes together; and although the <hi>Turkes</hi> wan, yet their loſſe was greateſt; for of them there fell 4000, and of the Chriſtians 17000 In the yeere 1449. <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> overthrew the <hi>Baſha Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtapha</hi> the ſecond time, in which fight 10000. <hi>Turkes</hi> were ſlaine, and <hi>Muſtapha</hi> was taken priſoners with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of their Commanders: after that in a ſkirmiſh fought by <hi>Moſes,</hi> (<hi>Scanderbegs</hi> Lieutenant) 2000. <hi>Turkes</hi> were ſlaine, 1000. Horſes taken, with the loſſe of 22. Chriſtians. In the ſame yeare likewiſe <hi>Amurath</hi> himſelfe went in perſon with a huge Army of 300000. into <hi>Epirus,</hi> where <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> with his owne hands in a fight ſlew the Generall <hi>Feri Baſſa,</hi> with 7000. <hi>Turkes,</hi> ſo for that time <hi>Amurath</hi> went backe with his Army: but the next yeere 1450. he return'd againe with 160000 Horſe and Foote, and at one Aſſault of the City of <hi>Croya</hi> in <hi>Epirus,</hi> the <hi>Turkes</hi> loſt 8000. men. <hi>Amurath</hi> being dead, his Sonne (<hi>Mahomet</hi> the great) ſent an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my into <hi>Epirus,</hi> under the leading of a valiant <hi>Turke</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Ameſa,</hi> whom <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> met, fought withall, and tooke Priſoner, with many other brave Comanders, and in that fight alſo 7000. <hi>Turkes</hi> were ſlaine, 1464.</p>
            <p>Much about the ſame time, the famous Prince <hi>Huni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ades,</hi> beate the Turkes Fleete in <hi>Manubius,</hi> neare to the City of <hi>Belgrade</hi> in <hi>Hungaria,</hi> where he tooke twenty of their Ships and Gallyes; many were ſunke and ſpoyl'd, and the reſt ranne a ground, and ſired themſelves, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they would not fall into the hands of the <hi>Huni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ades.</hi> Furthermore, in the ſame yeare 1464, <hi>Mahomet</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:3022:12"/>ſent his Generall <hi>Debreas,</hi> againſt <hi>Scanderbeg,</hi> betwixt whom was a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mell battaile fought, for <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> with his owne hand did encounter with <hi>Debreas</hi> in the hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt of the fight, and ſlew him, and tooke many Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, beſides 4120 of the Turkes were ſlaine. After that, <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> beſieged the Turkes in <hi>Belgrade,</hi> and put them to much diſtreſſe: but <hi>Mahomet</hi> came to raiſe the Siege, wherein a battaile was fought, and <hi>Scander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beg</hi> had the worſt, but the Turkes loſt 3000 men.</p>
            <p>In the ſame yeare alſo 1464, <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> met with the Traitor <hi>Moſes,</hi> (who was revolted lately from him to ſerve the Turke) and after a great and bloody fight, <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> was beaten, and fled, with the loſſe of 11000 men, and many Priſoners taken by <hi>Scanderbeg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There never were ſo many noble victories wonne in one yeare againſt the Turke, as were in this, 1464, and by ſuch brave Commanders as were <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> and <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niades,</hi> whoſe powers and force were ſo ſmall and weak, in reſpect of the numerous Armies of their Enemies, that the Turkes did contemne them; beſides <hi>Moſes</hi> (a valiant noble Commander) revolted from <hi>Scanderbeg,</hi> and ſerved the Turke againſt him; and after that <hi>Ameſa</hi> (<hi>Scanderbegs</hi> Nephew) likewiſe fled from him, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe came, with <hi>Iſaack</hi> the great Baſſa, with 50000 men, againſt him into <hi>Epirus,</hi> and there in the Plaine of <hi>Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalia</hi> the Turkes were overthrowne, the Baſſa put to flight, the Traitor <hi>Ameſa,</hi> with many of the Turkiſh Nobility and Commanders taken Priſoners, and thirty thouſand Turks ſlaine, and twenty of their braveſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes taken, the rich and ſtately Pavilions, Tents, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and munition, were all left as a reward to the vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> and his ſouldiers, who loſt but 60 men in that daies battaile.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:3022:13"/>
            <p>The Turkiſh Emperour thus often put to the worſt, made a peace with <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> for one yeare, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing expired, hee ſent <hi>Sinan Beg</hi> with 20000 men into <hi>Epirus,</hi> who was wholly diſcomfitted and made flee, with the loſſe of 17000: After that came <hi>Aſſam Beg,</hi> with 30000 horſe and foote, who was alſo overcome, and taken priſoner by <hi>Scanderbeg,</hi> and 21000 Turkes ſlaine: And after him came <hi>Iuſſum Beg</hi> with 1800 men, who was alſo beaten, and fled with much loſſe: And in ſhort time after <hi>Caraza Beg,</hi> with a mighty po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, of whom, in a ſharp conflict was ſlaine 4000 Turks, and <hi>Caraza</hi> was inforced to retire to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> with diſgrace.</p>
            <p>Then was a peace concluded betwixt <hi>Mahomet</hi> and <hi>Scanderbeg,</hi> which laſted not long, for the Turkes began to injure the <hi>Epirots;</hi> which <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> ſo much diſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, that he made inroads into their Territories, and having made a great havock amongſt them, returned with rich ſpoyles and priſoners.</p>
            <p>In revenge whereof, <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſent <hi>Seremet Baſſa,</hi> with 14000 Horſe and Foote, who was likewiſe beaten, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny rich Turkiſh Priſoners taken, and 1000 men ſlaine. After that, <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſent <hi>Ballabanus,</hi> three ſeverall times, with three ſeverall Armies, who were all overthrowne by <hi>Scanderbeg,</hi> one after another, with the loſſe of 12000 Turkes.</p>
            <p>For which overthrowes, <hi>Mahomet</hi> (being enraged) ſent the ſaid <hi>Ballabanus</hi> againe, and one <hi>Iacup, Arnauth,</hi> with two Armies, that they might by ſeverall wayes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade <hi>Epirus,</hi> and diſtreſſe <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> with which two Armies <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> fought, and put <hi>Ballabanus</hi> firſt to flight, and his army to rowt, after which,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3022:13"/>he ſlew <hi>Iacup,</hi> the other Generall, with his owne hand in fight, in theſe two battailes 24000 Turkes were ſlaine, and 6000 taken Priſoners.</p>
            <p>And thus in the compaſſe of one yeare, 1464, <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> with his ſmall Armies (for he was never above 20000, ſometimes but 6000, and many times fewer) ſlew 116000 Turkes, beſide the numbers of Priſoners that hee tooke.</p>
            <p>In the yeare 1465, <hi>Mahomet</hi> himſelfe went with an Army of 20000 againſt <hi>Scanderbeg,</hi> and returned backe againe, not doing any thing worth the noting, leaving behinde him his Generall <hi>Ballabanus,</hi> with 80000 men and horſe. After that, <hi>Mahomet</hi> was ſo malignant againſt <hi>Scanderbeg,</hi> that he hired two Turkes to goe into his Kingdome, and to bee turned Chriſtians, becauſe under that faire pretence they ſhould worke ſome meanes to poyſon him, which Turks were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed, their treachery diſclos'd, and <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> preſerved, and the Traitors executed.</p>
            <p>The Turkiſh Tyrant perceiving that all his forces and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies prevailed not againſt this moſt glorious, happy, and fortunate Prince; after which damnable plot, and auſpicious eſcape, <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> encountered with <hi>Iovima,</hi> a brother to <hi>Ballabanus,</hi> and <hi>Hedar</hi> his ſonne, and after a bloody bickering he tooke them, and many more priſoners, and following his Victory, he ſlew <hi>Ballabanus,</hi> the Turkiſh Generall: (his old Fugitive, and Renegado enemy) but for the number of the ſlaine it is not mentioned. And laſt of all, in the yeare 1466, <hi>Mahomet</hi> with another huge armie entred <hi>Epirus,</hi> with no better ſucceſſe than before he had; ſo that after the expence of much Treaſure, and many men loſt, he was glad to retire home againe to <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> and within ſhort time after the moſt illuſtrious Prince <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> dyed of a Feaver, ſo that his miſcreant enemies could not boaſt that they over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3022:14"/>came him, or were the death of him; but God, under whoſe Banner he had many times couragiouſly fought, was ſo gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious unto him, as to take him from this tranſitory life by a Naturall death.</p>
            <p>After the deceaſe of <hi>Scanderbeg, Mathias</hi> King of <hi>Hungria,</hi> the ſonne of that famous <hi>Huniades,</hi> before named, was ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Goad in the ſide of the proud Turk, for he wonne from him the Kingdome of <hi>Boſna,</hi> and a great part of the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pality of <hi>Servia,</hi> both which he joyned to the Kingdome of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> he was as fearefull a bug-Beare to the Turkes, as either <hi>Scanderbeg,</hi> or his father <hi>Huniades</hi> were before him; he ſlew <hi>Iſa,</hi> a great Commander under <hi>Mahomet,</hi> with 30000 common Souldiers, and others: the Turkes were a 100000 ſtrong, but the Chriſtians were not one quarter of that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; yet that Heroick Prince (by the aſſiſtance of God) got that glorious victory, with the loſſe of 8000 of his ſouldiers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Selimus</hi> the firſt, had his hands ſo full with the <hi>Perſians, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians, Arabians,</hi> and other of thoſe Eaſtern and <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metan</hi> Nations, that (as is ſaid before) he troubled not the Chriſtians, not they did not win or loſe much by him.</p>
            <p>His ſonne <hi>Soliman</hi> (the <hi>Magniſicent</hi>) beſieged <hi>Gunza</hi> a weake Towne, on the borders of <hi>Auſtria</hi> and <hi>Steirmarke,</hi> with 500000 men, and 3000 Peeces of Braſſe Ordnance: but after one Moneths ſiege, and thirteene fierce aſſaults, he was faine to raiſe his Campe, with the loſſe of a great number of his men, and leave <hi>Gunza</hi> untaken.</p>
            <p>In the yeare 1529, <hi>Soliman,</hi> the <hi>Magnificent,</hi> came in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to beſiege the City of <hi>Vienna,</hi> in <hi>Auſtria:</hi> (which City may well be called the Bulwarke of Chriſtendome) The Turkes beleagured it with 300000 men, which City was ſo valiant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defended, that after many aſſaults, breaches, minings, and moſt furious batteries, <hi>Soliman</hi> was glad to leave the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3022:14"/>Siege with the loſſe of 80000. of his <hi>Turkes,</hi> and many Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, with much Powder, Shot, and Ammunition ſpent, and all to little or ſmall purpoſe.</p>
            <p>After that in the yeere 1565, he ſent <hi>Muſtapha Baſſa</hi> with an Army of 30000. Horſe and Foote, and <hi>Piall Baſſa</hi> with a Fleete containing 180. Ships and Gallies, to mvade the Iſle of <hi>Malta;</hi> the <hi>Turkes</hi> being alſo ayded by the King of <hi>Algiers</hi> with 2200. men, 10. Galliots, and 7. Gallies, beſides 13. Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes, and 10. Galliots with 1600. men under the command of <hi>Bragut,</hi> (a famous Pirat) and after twelve moſt furious and bloody aſſaults (by the <hi>Turkes</hi>) by Sea and Land, the Iſland, Cities, and Caſtles of St. <hi>Elmo,</hi> St. <hi>Angelo,</hi> and St. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael</hi> being bravely defended by the Chriſtians ſixe Moneths, <hi>Muſtapha</hi> was forced with ſhame to leave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Malta,</hi> he having loſt in that expedition 24000. men. The whole Iſland of <hi>Malta</hi> is but 20. Miles in length, and 12. in bredth where it is broadeſt: and of the Knights of the Order, Gentlemen, Prieſts, Souldiers, Mariners, with all other men Inhabitants, as Artificers, and the like, they were not all in number above 12000 to repulſe and withſtand ſo great a power as the <hi>Turkes</hi> were: but <hi>Si Deus nobiſcum, quis contra nos?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare 1571, <hi>Selimus</hi> the ſecond ſent out a mighty Navy of Ships, Galleys, Frigots, and Brigandines, with a purpoſe to iuvade and over-runne Chriſtendome: Againſt whom many Chriſtian Princes joyned in a noble Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy; namely, the Pope, the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the Viceroy of <hi>Naples,</hi> the Dukes of <hi>Florence, Savoy;</hi> the Dukes of <hi>mantua, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbin,</hi> and <hi>Ferara;</hi> the Galleyes of <hi>Malta</hi> and <hi>Sicilia,</hi> the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netian</hi> Galleyes, and the Forces and perſonall ſervice of the valiant <hi>Alexander Ferveze</hi> Prince of <hi>Parma:</hi> Theſe Chriſtian Worthies with their Fleete united, the chiefe and generall Commander then being <hi>Dow John</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> (the ſecond
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3022:15"/>ſonne to <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth Emperour) a Prince of but twenty foure yeeres of age, but of an Heroick and invincible cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage: and after a moſt fierce and bloody battell many houres continued, the <hi>Turkes</hi> were beaten, 161. of their alleyes taken, more than 40. ſunke and fired, their Admirall <hi>Hali Baſſa</hi> ſlaine, with 32000. of his <hi>Turkes;</hi> many brave Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders taken priſoners, and 2956. of common men alſo taken; a great number of Chriſtians releaſed from ſlavery, (who were free'd being chain'd to row in the Gallies. Alſo 404. Peeces of Braſſe Ordnance were taken. This glorious Battell was fought neare the Gulph of <hi>Lepanto,</hi> the 7. of <hi>October,</hi> in the yeare 1471, in which famous Sea-fight there fell on the Chriſtian ſide of Commanders and others 7579. men. <hi>Lepanto</hi> was in ancient time a faire City of the <hi>Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> it was called <hi>Naupactum,</hi> it ſtandeth in <hi>Morea,</hi> (or <hi>Pelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poneſſus</hi>) it was wonne from the Chriſtians by <hi>Scander Baſſa,</hi> Generall to <hi>Bajazet</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Anno</hi> 1449.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Selimus</hi> the ſecond (the ſonne of <hi>Soliman</hi>) is ſpoken of before, and <hi>Amurath</hi> his ſonne that ſucceeded him, had ſo much to doe with the <hi>Perſian</hi> and other <hi>Aſian</hi> Princes, ſo that the Chriſtians were not troubled with him to any pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but onely with menaces and threatnings.</p>
            <p>In the yeare 1596. <hi>Mahomet</hi> the third was beaten by <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias</hi> the Arch-duke, neare <hi>Agria</hi> in <hi>Hungaria,</hi> the <hi>Turkes</hi> Emperour fled, with <hi>Ibrahim</hi> his great <hi>Baſſa,</hi> and in that fight 60000. <hi>Turkes,</hi> and 20000. Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Thus may any reaſonable Reader perceive, that the <hi>Turke</hi> hath received many overthrows from the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and with ſmall numbers have repulſed and beaten their multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes in deſpight of their boaſting and blaſphemous threats and Letters.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3022:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
